Imagine not having to put
a limit on yourself,
based on your need for an income.
Not letting the obligation
that you have to do this or that,
or you won't have food
to put on the table,
or a roof over your head,
control your choices.
If you had the basics taken care of,
- food, clothing, shelter, health -
what would you spend your days doing?
What's the first thing
that comes to your mind?
If you want to start a business,
develop a new idea,
devote yourself to your art,
or dedicate your life to helping others,
how much opportunity do you have to do so?
How much time and energy left over
after eight hours at work
and two in a commute?
How much freedom
after bankrupting that business
you finally took a chance at starting?
If it fails, that might
very well be the end of it,
your last chance to live your dream
gone into debt and disillusionment.
For those of us who have no fallback,
no economic safety net,
the stress that gives rise to,
is a burden we carry with us
in all that we do.
What a difference it could make
if we were able to set that burden down.
What a difference it would make
if we were able
to take a chance and mess up
and know that our bills
would still get paid,
because making mistakes
is far more valuable
than we give it credit for.
Failure is inherent in all learning.
The path to mastery
is through constant failure
and constant readjustment
in response to that failure,
again, and again, and again.
What if all those who failed,
and had to go back to their day jobs,
had gotten a second, a third, a fourth,
a perpetual chance even.
Where would we be today?
Cancer cured, flying cars,
a colony on Mars?
The world that I imagine
as a result of this thought experiment
is a world that I believe we can reach.
But the only way to reach it
is if people are truly free.
The type of freedom
that comes from equal opportunities
and the ability to make choices,
based on not what you have
to do to survive,
but what you want to do to thrive.
We could do this by providing
a universal basic income to everyone.
Now, in its simplest form,
the idea of a universal basic income
means that everyone should receive
an amount of money
sufficient to make ends meet,
regardless of their circumstances,
like employment,
social status, or even need.
Then, those who are able,
or wish to supplement their income,
are then free to take
any work that they choose.
The income they receive from that work
would be an addition
to their universal basic income,
- after taxes, of course.
The basic income is unconditional
in that nothing you do or don't do
will affect you receiving it.
It enshrines the principle
that we are all valued members
of these human societies
we've created all over the world.
We have a right to share
in their collective wealth.
The philosopher, Thomas Paine,
in 1797 wrote a pamphlet
called "Agrarian Justice,"
where he makes an argument
for universal basic income.
He states that,
"The earth in its natural,
uncultivated state
was and ever would have continued to be
the common property of the human race."
He goes on to say,
"It is the value of the improvement only
and not of the earth itself
that is individual property,
and that the proprietor, therefore,
of cultivated lands,
owes to the community a ground rent
for the land which he holds."
Now, the idea that we should all receive
a dividend from our stake
and our shared ownership
of the planet's resources
is a powerful one,
and an important one for the future.
A future where technological advances
with machine learning and automation
are poised to greatly
disrupt our societies
and create an ever deepening inequality.
To counter this, we must find a way
to sever the connection
between work and income.
I believe that we have
a unique opportunity to do just that,
and at the same time, do away
with that very stress
of having to make ends meet
by working a job that, essentially,
a robot could do better.
A report published by Carl Benedikt Frey
and Michael Osborne of Oxford University
found that 47 percent of US jobs
are at risk of automation
in the next decade or two.
In poorer countries like India,
69 percent of jobs are at risk.
In China, 77 percent.
A report published
by the World Economic Forum
argues that job losses could be offset
by employment growth in other areas,
but comes to the conclusion
that the rise of robots will still lead
to a net loss of over five million jobs
in 15 major developed
and emerging economies,
by 2020.
These aren't just factory jobs
that we're talking about here.
Those jobs are already mostly gone
in the western world.
We're talking about cashiers,
telemarketers,
jobs in insurance and the food industry,
serving, office and administrative jobs,
sales, transportation
- the list goes on.
The power of machine learning
means that the jobs people thought
would be safe from automation
are now at risk too.
Katja Grace from Oxford's
Future of Humanity Institute
led a study asking the world's leading
researchers in artificial intelligence
when they think artificial intelligence
will be better than human beings
at a wide range of tasks.
North American researchers estimate
that this will happen in 74 years.
But their Asian counterparts
see this happening in just 30 years.
However you look at it,
before long AI will outsmart humans
in almost everything.
I think 30 years is a reasonable estimate,
but there are important factors
in slowing down automation.
One of those is likely
the cheapness of labor.
Think how difficult the fight
for higher wages will be in the future
where technology offers cheaper and more
efficient results than human labor.
In our current economic model
where income, and therefore survival,
is dependent on having a job,
workers will have
very little leverage to negotiate
as wages will be driven down
by the constant threat
of either outsourcing
to a cheaper labor force overseas,
or to robots.
In our current economic model,
who benefits from automation?
In the past,
the main benefactors
of technological advances
have been businesses, industry.
Technology has made
the world richer overall, yes,
but not everyone has benefited.
In 2009, the top 1 percent
owned 44 percent of the world's wealth.
In 2014, they had 48 percent.
By 2020, it is estimated
that the 1 percent will own
54 percent of global wealth.
Now, this concentration of wealth,
it doesn't have to continue,
we can change the system.
For the first time in history,
technology could lead us
to the abundance necessary
to enrich humanity on an individual level.
To get there,
we have to be brave and open-minded enough
to dream a better world,
and then take the steps
towards that world.
Right now, automation is a threat,
but it doesn't have to be.
With a universal basic income,
it could be our road to freedom.
To buy that freedom,
we need to stop running our economy
on the ideologies of the past
and start designing
the economy of the future.
Now, there are many ways
that we could fund
a universal basic income.
Most of them involve taxation reforms
that are sorely needed in our shifting,
highly technical, globalized economy.
We could, as Thomas Paine suggested,
start thinking differently
about the private ownership of land,
or even the resources
that we all need to survive.
We could start thinking differently
about innovation
and the ownership of ideas,
or the ownership of data
that we give freely to large corporations
who then profit from it,
or the ownership
of technological progress,
which has been driven
by centuries of interchanging ideas.
Many of the technical wonders
that we enjoy in our everyday lives,
like computers and smartphones,
are based on research
that, to some degree,
has been taxpayer funded
and are produced with resources,
many of them rare minerals,
that are sourced from
the very ground we all walk.
How should these profits be shared?
There's also mounting evidence
through the many experiments
that have been done
with universal basic income
all over the world,
that the system leads
to lower crime rates,
lower school dropout rates,
fewer accidents
and stress related illnesses,
whilst increasing the level
of education and entrepreneurship.
These findings,
along with the removal
of the burdens and bureaucracy
that comes with our current
welfare system,
would lead to massive savings
in taxpayer money
that could be diverted
into funding a universal basic income.
Now, these are just a few ideas.
They may seem implausible
or impossible even,
but where there's a will,
there's a way, no?
To better understand
where we are today and how we got here,
it is important to delve into the past
and to understand that the systems
that frame our lives
are man-made.
We can change them.
Our current man-made system is designed
to reach a goal grounded in ideology
that is today at odds
with an equitable and sustainable future.
That goal is maximum growth
of the economy.
In perpetuity, Adam Smith,
who's been coined
The Father of Modern Capitalism,
had a clear idea of how to get there,
of how to reach that goal,
by maximizing worker efficiency
and as a result,
production and consumption.
By breaking down complex processes
into many tiny steps,
each allotted to one worker,
human beings became little more
than cogs in the industrial machine,
whose output was an imagined
infinite economic growth.
It's interesting to note
that Adam Smith himself
pointed out the downfall of a system,
which in effect, employs human beings
into mindless drudgery
for half of their working life,
in order for them to make ends meet.
He warned that forcing individuals
to perform mundane and repetitive tasks
would lead to an ignorant
and dissatisfied workforce.
This was, it seems,
an acceptable side effect,
as the goal was, after all,
the material wealth of nations
and not an enlightened
and content population.
Smith, he believed monetary incentives
to be vital to get people to work.
After all, why would anyone choose
the hard and repetitive toil
that offer in the factories of his day,
if it wasn't absolutely
necessary for survival?
The preconception was
that human beings are, in essence,
lazy and to some degree untrustworthy,
unless incentivized monetarily
to be otherwise.
The same school of thought
was then applied to our education system,
where instead of money, exam scores,
and degrees, and certificates
are used to incentivize learning,
as well as being pre-requisites
for graduating and then finding a job.
From an early age, we become accustomed
to working for extrinsic,
rather than intrinsic rewards.
Instead of being motivated
from that feeling of accomplishment,
when you come to understand concepts
and their application in the world,
that eureka moment,
when you finally get something.
Instead of that,
we're motivated to memorize
words and labels,
repeating them like a parrot,
to pass that exam, get that degree,
and contribute to that common goal,
endless economic growth.
What's wrong with that?
Hasn't it served to make
all of our lives a lot more wealthy?
Yes, it has.
At least, materially it has,
but it's also led to, as Smith warned,
an uninformed, dissatisfied population
forever seeking extrinsic validation
and instant gratification.
The perfect consumer.
Pollution of land, sea, and air
are the other fruits of this
low cost approach to civilization,
where we consume more
with every passing year,
as if this planet
were actually expanding in step.
Many of the conditions
that make this planet beautiful,
bountiful, and capable
of sustaining human life
are facing threats so far gone,
that our current technology
might not be able to deal with them,
even if we made
a concerted effort to do so,
which we are not.
Despite this,
our measure for success and well-being
is still Gross Domestic Product.
The amount of stuff we produce
without any regard to actual need,
making our economic system work
against the very systems we rely on
for our survival and well-being.
What does this tell us?
Do we not have to rethink
our very definition of success?
What makes a nation truly wealthy?
I believe that to find these answers,
we have to be willing
to examine our core belief systems
and ask ourselves if they're serving us.
By us, I mean all of us,
because if we're to evolve as a species,
we must rise above the individual interest
and start looking towards the interest
of the collective, the whole.
Our world is fast changing, and with it,
the societies and the systems
that we've built to sustain us.
Now, these changes will happen
with or without our participation.
It's not a question of if,
but of when and how.
The how is something
we have a little control over,
but only to the extent
of how willing we are
to look at the paths ahead,
understand the inevitable changes we face,
and to prepare.
We must prepare.
These will be the deciding factors
and whether a particular change
will be positive or negative for society.
Now, the how might very well be
a universal basic income,
which has the potential
to both mitigate unemployment,
greatly accelerate the rate
of technological development,
possibly save the planet,
and make people be more fulfilled
and happy than they have ever been.
Now, I think that's worth a shot.
Don't you?
Thank you.
[applause]